Nikola Tesla sees a wireless vision by Anonymous, the New York Times, 3rd October, 1915.
This is a LibriVox recording.
All LibriVox recordings are in the public domain.
For more information or to volunteer, please visit LibriVox.org.
Nikola Tesla sees a wireless vision.
Things his world system will allow hundreds to talk at once through the Earth.
Trans-static disturbance.
Inventor hopes also to transmit pictures by the same medium which carries the voice.
Nikola Tesla announced to the Times last night that he had received a patent on an invention
which would not only eliminate static interference, the present bugaboo of wireless telephony,
but would enable thousands of persons to talk at once between wireless stations and make
it possible for those talking to see one another by wireless regardless of the distance separating
them.
He said also that with his wireless station, now in the process of construction on Long
Island, he hoped to make New York one of the central exchanges in a world system of
wireless telephony.
Mr. Tesla has been working on wireless problems for many years.
Yesterday he exhibited an article published in the Electrical World 11 years ago in which
he predicted not only wireless telephony on a commercial basis, but that it would be possible
to identify the voice of an acquaintance over any distance.
That its operator in Hawaii was able to distinguish the voice of an engineer friend at Arlington,
Virginia, was announced by the American Telephone and Telegraph Company as the most marked triumph
of its communication by wireless telephone from the Naval radio station at Arlington
to Pearl Harbor, Hawaii, a distance of 4,000 miles.
The inventor, who has won fame by his electrical inventions, dictated this statement yesterday.
The experts carrying out this brilliant experiment are naturally deserving of great credit for
the skill they have shown in perfecting the devices.
These are of two kinds, first, those serving to control transmission, and second, those
magnifying the received impulse.
That the control of transmission is perfect is plain to experts, from the fact the Arlington,
Maryland, and Pearl Harbor plants are all inefficient, and that the distance of telephonic
transmission is equal to that of telegraphic transmission.
It is also perfectly apparent that the chief merit of the application lies in the magnification
of the microphonic impulse.
It must not be imagined that we deal here with new discoveries.
The improvement simply concerns the control of the transmitted and the magnification of
the received impulse, but the wireless system is the same.
This can never be changed.
That it is practicable to project the human voice not only to a distance of 5,000 miles,
but clear across the globe, I demonstrated by experiments in Colorado in 1899.
Among my publications, I would refer to an article in the electrical world of March 5,
1904, but describing really tests I made in 1899.
The facts which I pointed out in the article were of much greater significance than that
of the experiments reported, although this should be taken in a scientific sense, as
the experiments were simply scientific demonstrations.
I pointed out then that the modulations of the human voice can be reproduced more clearly
through the earth than through wire.
It is difficult for the layman to understand, but it is an absolute fact that transmission
through the earth with a proper apparatus is not more difficult than the sending of
a message on a wire strung across a room.
This wonderful property of the planet, that, electrically speaking, is through its very
bigness small, is of incalculable significance for the future of mankind.
These tests made between Washington and Honolulu will act as an immense stimulus to wireless
telephony and would be of much more value to the world if the principles of the transmission
were understood, but they are not.
Even now, fifteen years after the fundamental principles have been demonstrated and the
possibility shown, there are many experts in the dark.
For instance, it is claimed that static disturbances will fatally interfere with the transmission,
while, as a matter of fact, there is no static disturbance possible in properly designed
transmission and receiving circuits.
Quite recently I have described in a patent circuits which are absolutely immune to static
and other interferences, so much so that when a telephone is attached, there is absolute
silence, even lightning in the immediate vicinity not producing a click of the diaphragm, while
in the ordinary telephonic conversation there are all kinds of noises.
Transmission without static interference has many wonderful properties besides, first of
which is that unlimited amounts of power can be transmitted with very small loss.
Another contention is that there can be no secrecy in wireless telephone conversation.
I say it is absurd to raise this contention when it is positively demonstrated by experiments
that the earth is more suitable for transmission than any wire could ever be.
A wireless telephone conversation can be made as secret as thought.
I have myself erected a plant for the purpose of connecting by wireless telephone the chief
centers of the world, and from this plant, as many as a hundred, will be able to talk
absolutely without interference and with absolute secrecy.
This plant would simply be connected with a telephone central exchange of New York City,
and any subscriber will be able to talk to any other telephone subscriber in the world,
and all this without any change in the apparatus.
This plan has been called my world system.
By the same means, I propose also to transmit pictures and project images so that the subscriber
will not only hear the voice, but see the person to whom he is talking.
Pictures transmitted over wires is a perfectly simple art practiced today.
Many inventors have labored on it, but the chief credit is due Professor Korn of Munich.
His apparatus can be attached to a wireless plant, and at any other wireless plant can
be reproduced.
I have undertaken this in the hope of establishing a service which would greatly facilitate the
work of the press.
A picture could be sent from a battlefield in Europe to New York in five minutes if the
proper instruments were available.
A further advantage would be that transmission is instant and free of the unavoidable delay
experienced with the use of wires and cables.
As I have already made known, the current passes through the earth, starting from the
transmission station with infinite speed, slowing down to the speed of light at a distance
of 6,000 miles, then increasing in speed from that region, and reaching the receiving station
again with infinite velocity.
It's all a wonderful thing.
Wireless is coming to mankind in its full meaning like a hurricane some of these days.
Some day there will be, say, six great wireless telephone stations in a world system connecting
all the inhabitants on this earth to one another, not only by voice, but by sight.
It's surely coming.
End of Nikola Tesla sees a wireless vision by Anonymous, The New York Times, 3rd October
1915.